[Music]
we shall start the last chapter of this
course this week and we'll devote most
of the week to this last
chapter the last chapter is an
application of ology topological methods
rather to dynamical systems have you
heard of dynamical
systems you
haven't you have been doing mathematics
for a long time surely you have heard of
dynamical
systems dynamical systems are in some
sense a modern growth of differential
equations you know
nowadays except Elementary courses and
except the beginning student nobody
tries to solve a differential
equation because all the solvable
differential equations have been solved
we know all the
tricks rather the challenge when given
an differential equation when you model
something in terms of differential
equation is to extract
Solutions or rather extract information
about the solution without solving the
differential
equation how what can you say about the
behavior of the solution without writing
down the
answer that's a much more powerful
approach and that's what we do nowadays
with differential equations and that
point of view is called differential
equation not differential equations you
see I'm not awake yet it's too early
that point of view is dynamical systems
okay so as such it is really a vast and
very powerful field in fact it's not
quite a field it's basically all of
science but that's what dynamical
systems are because you know everything
that we study in nature in society what
have you evolve in time and we want to
keep track of how the system evolves in
terms of time so with that preliminary
I'm going to start the
discussion most of the discussion will
be concerned with equilibria in
dynamical systems but the topological
ideas can be applied to many other
features of dynamical
[Applause]
systems now there is
something
tricky difficult in this application at
the outset in the beginning and that is
how we visualize a vector field
the elementary method is given a vector
field for example on the plane for
example in space but on more General
surfaces and manifolds to draw lots and
lots of arrows I hope that you're
familiar with vecta Fields because you
learned multivariable characters in your
education usually you draw lots and lots
of arrows but there is an alternative
method which turns out to be important
for application of topology and it is
the method of visualizing a vector field
by its graph now what do we mean by this
here is an
example let us
visualize the vector field that
corresponds to the differential
equation which
is like
this please note that although yes in
some Elementary textbooks Elementary
courses you might have been writing Dy
DX all the time modern mathematicians
today's mathematicians around the world
all almost always write DX
DT so the independent variable is T we
think of it as time okay and dependent
variable is X so please do not be
confused X is not the independent
variable X is the dependent variable so
if you have been writing D Dy DX all
your lives you should change your
Viewpoint or notation so that's the
vector field you see the right hand side
gives you this rate of change of the
left hand
side there are two
possibilities you have a
question yes
somebody I heard the voice maybe I was I
what do you mean x equal
Z no you mean is this equal zero yeah no
no have you ever seen a differential
equation in your
life no but maybe some people may not
have I don't I'm just assuming that
people have but maybe my assumption is
wrong have you seen a differential
equation in your life can you write down
a differential equation one differential
equation any differ equation
please can you come come on come on I
don't have we don't have time to waste
so maybe you can
dictate any differential equation let's
go okay then you have never seen a
differential equation in your life if I
ask you to write down any example and
you cannot it can be a simple example it
can be an a trival example and you
cannot that means that you have never
seen a differential equation in your
life in which case we should discuss the
matter later because you have never seen
a differential equation in my life I
should try to teach you some
differential equation later but so you
cannot write down any differential
equation at all you you say your
reaction is I don't know is that is that
what it is is that the end of the
discussion I don't think so I don't
think so you're wasting your opportunity
I I don't think you should waste the
opportunity but unless you respond a bit
more quickly
yeah you know you know alaz it's not
just you it's about most other
people you know I have we have to spend
usually 10 minutes persuading the
student to say what they
know 10 minutes whereas they could have
said it in 10 seconds and that means
that we can do so so little during the 3
weeks if you just say what you know we
can do so much more so let's not waste
time because
really I love your company but I'm not
here for long you know I go away and
that's goodbye so do you know any
differential equation yes have you seen
any differential equation yes can you
write down any differential equation
just give me one differential equation
any differential equation please
okay so that's a differential equion you
said that you didn't
know two minutes two minutes ago right
do you realize what's happening yes you
are shy yes it's funny oh yes now you
you say that you know but you know those
two minutes are
gone right in fact it's more than 3
minutes now do you do you know what's
happening you what's happening is that
if you're going to leave you know a life
you can instead of doing mathematics and
instead of achieving so much because
instead of doing things in 10 seconds
you insist on doing things in 10 minutes
that's a factor of 60 well if you are
going to be be active for 60 years in
mathematics you can achieve only what is
worth for one year
so really we should change the attitude
and get going yeah it's not just just
you it's about everyone at as I often
find that people are very intelligent
very hardworking and very nice but
really the teachers must sort of ask
them and ask them and ask them for 10
minutes before they say what they know
please get going quickly yes you
understand what I'm saying I hope so so
this is a differential
equation so do you think that you always
put it equal to zero
no why not well because that's what you
want to solve and that's your
relationship you are not suddenly saying
ah this is a polinomial and whenever I
see a polinomial I think it's an
algebraic equation so I'm going to write
it down to zero right so we don't appri
put it equal to zero that's the
differential equation so far but
interestingly it is interesting to look
at the case when this is equal to zero
now I cannot find the Eraser what's
going
on why did it end up there it's very
strange next time I'm going to find it
there next time in the other room
and
Mysteries
okay okay let's not waste any more
time we'll
see equals z in a moment you are
thinking equal Z because of equilibria
probably but that's slightly later so
let's visualize this differential
equation or rather the dynamical system
or rather the vector field
okay here is how
you visualize
it 3
point0 and plus -
one and
here if I'm at this point H let's draw
an arrow at this point let's draw the
velocity what's the velocity somewhere
here well if I'm at the point for
example 2 the velocity is x = 2 so 2 *
2^ 2 - 1 whatever that is it's six so
it's pointing in this direction what I'm
going to write draw is something like
this so if I go further out it's much
longer but anyway in this part of the
picture I'm moving right
clear in this part of the picture it's
easy to check I'm moving left and this
part of the picture I'm moving right and
this part of the picture I'm again
moving
left okay what if I am at one of those
points 0
1 and minus
one those
points what is the velocity Vector at
those points and you can it's zero
H do you see that that's 0 minus + one
this right hand side becomes zero so
these are what is called
equilibria the that is
the velocity
field let's write not velocity field so
Vector field is
zero um
velocity at these
points is zero and that means that if
you put the
point here the point will not
move okay so that's what it
means okay so that's what an equilibri
equilibrium is and that's why our friend
was asking about putting that equal to
zero but initially what we are studying
is the behavor behavior of this now
there is an alternative way of thinking
about this so that was the x-axis the
alternative way is quite nice too let's
draw the
graph of V of X in terms of X when I say
a graph people always want
to intersect the two axis but in this
case for a reason that you see it's much
better to write the vertical axis on the
side not in the middle so the one
possible picture is just directory like
this but the other possible picture is
the following I
draw a
graph
of this function
so this is
VX um = X of x^2 -
5 okay so that's the
graph that's easy to draw right and then
you ask yourself what is happening first
of all there are three points where the
graph intersects the x- axxis what does
that mean it means that that those three
points naturally V is zero but what does
v0 mean it means that the velocity is
zero that means that you don't move at
those points so those are the
equilibria and then you ask yourself
again for example in this region between
minus 0 and 0 - one and 0 you see I'm
really not awake Min - one and 0 the
graph is positive
what does it mean it means that in this
part of the picture V is positive that
means that the velocity is pushing you
in a positive
direction is that
clear so here I'm going in this
direction because the graph is positive
here I'm going in this direction because
the graph is negative but this negative
value of the graph mean that means that
the VX the velocity or the vector field
is negative sign which means that the
velocity dxdt is negative which means
that I'm going this way so in a part of
the picture where the graph is hanging
down I go left and standing up I go
right how about here which way which
direction do I go right and you can see
that further I go the bigger the value
of V so I go faster and faster and here
of course I go left and I go faster
faster in the negative Direction Okay so
this and this those two pictures contain
exactly the same amount of information
but it turns out that this
picture will be
useful for
us for topological
[Applause]
applications so we shall be working with
this picture but please um always
um be able to translate between this
this picture
okay
good now that was in dimension one in
dimension greater than one in dimension
greater than
one graphing a vector field can be a
little tricky
[Applause]
so we have to do something
strange first let's um look at an
example in this
case Dimension two I'm going
to discuss a vector field
which looks like
this okay I hope you understand what
this
means I also should point out that in
textbooks and so on usually this V is
written as the gothic v um sort of thick
letter V and so on but on the black W
it's difficult to do so I'm going write
it like this some people put an arrow
over it but because we'll be writing
lots and lots of vector FS that becomes
Tome so I'm going to meet the arrow
you'll understand from the context what
this means let's draw the picture of
this Vector field in the usual way that
is in the first
way
okay how does this work well for example
at this point which way does the vector
Point Rosemary you can see that's X
that's Y at this point which way that's
the vector Point Vector Field Point
Point huh well positive means what in
that direction that's
positive huh
no what do you think X is and what do
you think Y is approximately I didn't
give you any minical values huh X is
zero I keep saying this
one just give some value of x
huh yeah for example somebody says xal 1
is there anything fundamentally wrong
with this no X1 or xal 1 that's okay
what's
y okay so what so what's the
vector what's the
vector what what's the vector the vector
is at this this point is this one so
what's the
vector yeah so what's the vector please
call out the components
and what's the second component you see
I have have to keep talking for 10
minutes before you say what you know
already Yes zero and one okay and which
way does it
point this
way the vector 01 which way you know
this this way Vector
01 try it once
again Vector Z one okay come to the
Blackboard come to the Black come to the
blackard come come come to the the black
please come to the black R
please starting at this point please
draw the vector
01 okay why do you look at me yes okay
good so Rosemary you knew this you kept
saying this way and that
way it's interesting that
we had to ask Rosemary to come to the
Blackboard and draw it until she said
what she knew it's quite interesting and
the reason is while you ask being asked
a question and you're responding to a
question you are not
active you're sitting there and saying
okay 1 2 A B C and so on maybe maybe you
are not really active but if you have to
stand in front of the entire class and
you have to do it you now become serious
okay now I have to solve this
problem and I know what the answer is so
I'm going to write it down well really
we should become serious from the
beginning and then you can move on so
much faster okay so and make progress
and make use of life so Zer is of course
pointing
up let's not be ridiculous so here the
vector you looks like this but rather
let me draw it to it right how about
here Vector field which way does it
Point silence which which way does the
vector Field
Point don't say negative negative means
what negative means this way
huh no no come on okay poting a s so at
this point please imagine what X and Y
are what are
they what's X what's y z and one 0er and
one okay so what's the vector what does
the vector look
like
yeah yeah zero X is z y is one that's
what you said I agree with you so what's
the vector at this
point
H can you speak a bit more loudly
because I cannot
hear pointing up along the y axis is
that what you you're saying is that what
you're saying if if x is zero and Y is 1
if x is Zer and Y is 1 that is the name
of this point at this point x is0 y is 1
what is the
vector 0 1 if x is z and y is
1 sorry yes I'm sorry
too you know again it took us a whole
minute to do this
let's get going shall we okay so it's
what are they- - one Z so which way does
the vector
Point
down minus one Z try again okay do you
want to come up up and then draw because
probably you can so which way does the
vector
Point good she's drawing on her own not
notebook and then she'll be able to do
it
which way does it
point do you remember what you just said
components minus one and zero you you do
it like this which way does it point
this towards the right is that what what
you
say okay come come come
with did you say the vector Min - one 0
that's what you said right please throw
that
back does it go
right okay so if I asked you plus one
and zero what would you
do yes I'm sorry too yes so which one is
the original
Vector S one last last time which one is
the original Vector it goes left okay
yeah you know this
already
right okay really we shouldn't have a
class at 8:30 in the
morning
okay okay it points
left can you guess what the rest of the
picture looks like tror can for example
here which way does few Point down okay
you're not TR but you're brilant and
here he points this way what which way
does the vector Field Point at this
position you think anybody going yeah
that's correct so it's going this way
and that's easy to figure out because
for example if the coordinates are one
and one something like that look it's
minus one and one I hope you can figure
out which way the vector field points
Vector points are for - one and one yeah
without taking 5 minutes minus one X
components in negative one y component
is positive so it's going to put Contra
this so this is what it looks like can
you say what this Vector field
does rotates it rotates that's what it
does okay so in
general if you want to draw a
trajectory of this uh solution curve to
this Vector field they are all circular
trajectories like this
and the effect of this differential
equation is take any initial condition
x0 and Y Z and just start rotating it
like
this okay so that's what it does that's
picture number
one picture number two is much more
abstract and it's going to be a little
confusing picture number two
tries to do what we did with the
graph but in order to draw this graph we
have to
have two dimensions for the position and
two dimensions for the velocity Vector
so we need four dimensional space which
we don't have so we are going to draw
the graph in a somewhat abstract
fashion this is the plane of V of XY and
this is the plane of XY
okay I hope you can be with me and here
we are going to draw this kind of
graph those
circles yeah can you see what I'm
drawing now in the middle I'm going to
plant lots and lots of different uh
things at this point which corresponds
to this
point what does the
value of the vector look like well it's
vertical
up
right you agree now at this
point at the origin what is the value of
the vector
field at the
origin come on it's zero in other words
it's an equilibrium to use the word that
we have just Le okay at zero you don't
move and at this point the next Point
let's say over
here I'm going to put lots and lots of
panels what's the vector field where
it's at this point so it's
pointing
right okay and at this point
that corresponds to that point it's
pointing left and so on and so on so
maybe at this point in the
back you cannot really see it but it's
pointing
down and so on so now you realize that
this is a very abstract picture and you
shouldn't trust it too
much let's draw it a little differently
so that I can see the arrow behind
it's kind of pointing it's pointing
down
okay we have to do this if we are to
draw the graph of this Vector field
because the graph would require 2 + two
four dimensional space so this is the
best we can do but I hope you understand
the idea of this graph which is that at
each point you figure out which way the
vector field is pointing in other words
what the value of that Vector field is
the value is a vector and so to each
point I associate a
vector so if we have this space for the
manifold and the set of vectors in the
vertical Direction vector vector space
then you can imagine some sort of graph
yeah like
this at each point I have a certain
value and that's the value Vector value
of the vector f